Guide to the George Heard Hamilton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Heard Hamilton Papers
1937-1966
MS 1145
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(3 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, course materials, writings, and newspaper clippings relating to George Heard Hamilton's career as a professor of art history, art gallery curator and administrator, and author. Correspondents include curators of U.S. and European art museums and galleries, colleagues at Yale and at other universities, and members of the international art community.
Hamilton, George Heard, 1910-2004
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University School of Art and Architecture in 1977.
Scope and Contents
The George Heard Hamilton Papers consist of correspondence, course materials, writings, and newspaper clippings relating to Hamilton's career as a professor of art history, art gallery curator and administrator, and author.
The alphabetically arranged correspondence, which forms the largest part of the collection, pertains to Hamilton's administrative and teaching activities at Yale; his involvement with educational art associations; and his writing of histories of art. Hamilton corresponded with curators of the Museum of Modern Art, the Art Institute of Chicago, the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, and other art museums and galleries regarding exhibits and illustrations for his publications; with colleagues at Yale and at other universities regarding administrative and professional activities; and with members of the international art community including Katherine Dreier, Man Ray, and Marcel Duchamp, the founders of the Sociètè Anonyme, whose collection catalogue Hamilton edited. (The papers of the Société Anonyme are in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.)
Folders containing course materials from Hamilton's art history courses, short writings, newspaper clippings relating to the 1937 donation of the Jules S. Bache art collection to the state of New York, and a notebook containing listings of Hamilton's collection of Tennyson first editions, form the remainder of the collection.
Biographical / Historical
GEORGE HEARD HAMILTON, 1910-2004
George Heard Hamilton was born in Pittsburg, Pennsylvania on June 23, 1910, the son of Frank Arthur and Georgia Heard Hamilton. He received a B.A. (1932), M.A. (1934), and Ph.D. (1942) from Yale University. He was a research associate at the Walters Art Gallery in Baltimore from 1934 to 1936, when he began his tenure at Yale as an instructor in art history. Hamilton was an assistant professor (1943-1947), associate professor (1947-1956), and professor (1956-1966) of art history, and curator of modern art at the Yale University Art Gallery (1940-1966). He was chairman of the Department of Art from 1959 to 1962, and associate director of the Art Gallery from 1946 to 1948. From 1963 to 1964 he was the Robert Sterling Clark visiting professor of art at Williams College in Williamstown, Massachusetts. From 1966 to 1975 he was a professor of art at Williams, and was the director of the Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute in Williamstown from 1966 to 1977. From 1966 to 1968 Hamilton was the president of the College Art Association of America.
Hamilton wrote Manet and his Critics (1954); Art and Architecture of Russia (1954); European Painting and Sculpture 1880-1940 (1967); with W. C. Agee Raymond Duchamp Villon (1967); and 19th and 20th Century Art: Painting, Sculpture, Architecture (1970). He edited the catalogue of the Collection of the Sociètè Anonyme which was published in 1950.
Hamilton died in Williamstown, Massachusetts, on March 29, 2004.
Art, Modern; Art historians; Educators; Man Ray, 1890-1976; Dreier, Katherine S. (Katherine Sophie), 1877-1952; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968; Hamilton, George Heard, 1910-2004; Art Institute of Chicago; College Art Association of America; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Art Gallery; Yale University. School of Art and Architecture. Dept. of Art History
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Art Gallery of Toronto, 1955, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Art Institute of Chicago, 1949, 1954-1955, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - A-An (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ar-Au (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bareiss, Walter, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Brainard, Frank S., 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ba-Be (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bi-Bu (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - College Art Association of America, 1952-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Columbia University, 1949, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - C-Ca (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Ch-Col (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Con-Cu (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Da-Do (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Dr-Du (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - E (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - F (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Ga-Gi (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Gl-Gu (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Harry N. Abrams, Inc., 1957-1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Harvard University, 1954-1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Harvard University Press, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Ha-Hay (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - He-Hu (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - I (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - John Simon Guggenheim Foundation, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - J (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - K (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - L (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York), 1953-1954, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Museum of Fine Arts (Boston), 1953-1964 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Museum of Modern Art (New York), 1953-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - M-Ma (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Me-Mr (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Mug-Mus (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Na-Newl (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Newy-No (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - O (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Penguin Books, Ltd., 1953-1955, 1961-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Pevsner, Nikolaus, 1953-1955, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1949, 1960-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Princeton University, 1956-1963 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - P-Pa (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Pe-Pu (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Q (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - R-Re (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Rh-Rog (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Ros-Ry (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Sidney Janis Gallery, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum (New York), 1956, 1961-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Sprague, Arthur, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Steefel, Lawrence, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute (Williamstown, MA), 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Sa-Sc (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Se-So (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Sp-Su (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - T (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - University of Illinois, 1949, 1954-1962 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - University of Pennsylvania, 1953-1965 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Un-University N (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - University O-University W (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - V (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Wadsworth Athenium (Hartford, CT), 1954-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art (New York), 1949, 1960-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Wittenboro and Company, 1950, 1956-1963 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - W-Wa (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - We-Wh (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Wic-Win (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Wo-Wu (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Yale University
      - Graduate School, 1953-1956, 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - Miscellaneous, 1953-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
      - Sterling Memorial Library, 1953-1962 (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - Yale Club of New York, 1956, 1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
      - Yale Russian Club, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      - Yale University Art Gallery, 1949, 1954-1956, 1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Yale University Press, 1954, 1960-1966 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Y - Z (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Unidentified, fragments, and notes (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Clippings: Bache art gift, 1937 April (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Course materials, 1949-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Notebook: record of his library as a Yale undergraduate, a collection of Tennyson first editions, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Writings, 1951-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)